

Nuno Miguel MARTINS PACHECO

LinkedIn: martinspacheco Homepage: www.nmmp.de E-mail: nuno.pacheco@outlook.de

PROFILE

I am a creative and determined project manager with over 6 years of experience in product development. Specialising in design thinking and agile methods, I have proven that I can translate customer needs into successful product strategies. I have a background in mechanical engineering and am currently completing my PhD in product development at TUM. During my time at university, I have worked in leading positions with industrial partners such as BMW, MAN and Siemens as well as academic partners such as Imperial College London. My passion is to have a positive impact on organisations and people through innovative projects and effective team leadership. I enjoy working in teams, taking responsibility and delivering projects that create real value for customers and organisations.

WORK EXPERIENCE

07/2019 - Current

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE

Technical University of Munich (TUM), Munich, Germany

10/2021 - Current

MCube STEAM in collaboration with BMW, MAN, SWM and Stanglmeier

- Co-Project Lead: Responsible for project progress monitoring, implemented regular progress reports and workshops that improved communication and collaboration with project partners
- Leading the concept development: Integrated bus system for passenger and parcel transport in public transport, which increased bus utilisation by ~20% and saved ~180 kg CO2 per bus line each day
- Leading the realisation of the VR demonstrator: Presented at the IAA Mobility 2023, which was tested by over 120 exhibition visitors and received ~90% positive feedback (technology acceptance survey)

07/2019 - Current

THINK. MAKE. START. in collaboration with BMW

- Co-organiser: Successful implementation of 6x one-week sprints to develop customer-centric, innovative products, with some projects receiving €50k budget through management support for further development as part of pre-development
- Coaching cross-functional teams: Teaching skills in prototyping, storytelling and design thinking, which improved employees' skills in cross-functional collaboration, customer understanding and innovative thinking

07/2019 - 03/2024

THINK. MAKE. START. in collaboration with UnternehmerTUM, Makerspace and Zeidler Research Association

- Project Lead: Successful organisation and implementation of 8x two-week sprints as a university seminar, which led to the creation of an average of one startup per sprint (e.g., Angsa Robotics) and received an average course rating of 1.1 from students (~400 students)
- Coaching interdisciplinary teams: Teaching skills in prototyping, storytelling, design thinking, and product strategy, enabling students to develop user-centred, economically viable products and enhance their innovative thinking abilities

02/2022 - Current

FREELANCER

Mintech Engineering GmbH, Garching, Germany

- Concept Developer & Workshop Instructor: Development and successful realisation of 4 newly designed, technology-focused design thinking and prototyping workshops for customers (e.g. BMW, Siemens), whose success was confirmed by positive customer feedback and follow-up projects
- Coaching cross-functional teams: Teaching skills in brainstorming, prototyping, storytelling, and design thinking, which significantly improved the
 problem-solving and innovation abilities of the participants

EDUCATION

09/2019 - Current

PhD. DOCTOR'S DEGREE, MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

Technical University of Munich (TUM), Munich, Germany

- Specialisation: Product development of mechatronics products, design sprints
- PhD Thesis: A Hackathon Approach for Design Education to Enable Quantitative Analysis of Effort Spent, Product Concept Quality, and Learning Effect in Technical Higher Education (Thesis submitted 05/2024)

12/2022 & 05/2023

VISITING RESEARCHER, DESIGN ENGINEERING

Imperial College London, London, England

10/2016 - 05/2019

M.Sc. MECHANICAL ENGINEERING AND MANAGEMENT

Technical University of Munich (TUM), Munich, Germany

- Specialisation: Product development, production and innovation
- Master Thesis: Prototyping Recommendation Framework; A Collection of Prototyping Methods for Early-Stage Product Development (Technical University of Denmark, 05/2019)

02/2018 - 06/2018

SEMESTER ABROAD, MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

Instituto Superior Técnico (IST), Lisbon, Portugal

10/2011 - 10/2011

B.Sc. MECHANICAL ENGINEERING AND ECONOMICS

Technical University of Graz (TUG), Graz, Austria

- Specialisation: Engineering sciences with a foundation in natural sciences and business economics
- Bachelor Thesis: Business Creation, Factors Influencing this Decision, and Importance of Entrepreneurial Universities

02/2002 - 06/2011

GENERAL HIGHER EDUCATION QUALIFICATION

Taunusgymnasium Königstein, Königstein im Taunus, Germany

KNOWLEDGE AND SKILLS

Language Skills

German (native), English (business fluent), Portuguese (native), Spanish (basic), Italian (basic)

IT Skills

MS Office (very good), Miro (very good), Adobe Creative Cloud (good), Notion (good), Trello (good), Confluence (very good), Jira (basic), Python (basic), R (good), Figma/Adobe XD (basic)

Special Skills

Design Thinking, project management, communication skills, problem solving skills, cross-functional collaboration, stakeholder management

OTHER

Memberships

Design Society (since 2019), Verein Deutscher Ingenieure (since 2023), Deutscher Alpenverein (since 2024)

Interests

Road Biking (e.g., Munich to Bozen), Hiking (Alps, Norway, Portugal), Vinyl (Rock, Ambient, Electronic), Analog Photography (Urban & Nature), Cooking (Italian, Portuguese), Hackathon Participation (Best concept Vitra Work 2019, Best Prototype TMS #6 2017)